Catalog of the Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts in The Yale Collection of American Literature, Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Published by The Walt Whitman Archive in collaboration with the University of Nebraska-Lincoln Libraries.
Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts in The Yale Collection of American Literature, Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
N/A
Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892
poetry prose Manuscripts
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library Yale University Library P.O. Box 208240 New Haven, Connecticut 06520-8240
This electronic catalog was created from catalog cards obtained by the Walt Whitman Archive. The original papers and catalog cards are held at The Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Restrictions on Original Materials:
Please consult with the repository.
Scope and Content
The Yale Collection of American Literature, Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library holds a variety of documents related to Walt Whitman, including drafts of poetry and prose, notes, letters, printed versions of Whitman compositions, and pieces written about Whitman by others. This catalog includes item-level descriptions of only those documents deemed poetry and prose manuscripts.
Biographical Information
Subjects
Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892; Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892--Manuscripts; Poets, American--19th century
Item List
- As in a Swoon, about 1876; yal.00004; xxx.00567; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box box 3)
  This is a manuscript of the poem As in a Swoon, first published in the 1876 printing of Leaves of Grass. Although this poem was not included in any subsequent editions of Leaves of Grass, Whitman did include it in the 1891 volume Good-Bye My Fancy, and as one of the few poems in the 1892 volume Complete Prose Works.
- By thine own lips, O Sea, about 1884; yal.00014; xxx.00340; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box box 3)
  This manuscript is a draft of the poem first published as With Husky-Haughty Lips, O Sea! in the March 1884 edition of Harper's Monthly Magazine. The poem was reprinted in the Sands at Seventy annex to the 1888 edition of Leaves of Grass. Whitman wrote this draft on the verso of a sheet of stationery for the Sheldon House of Ocean Grove, New Jersey.
- Fancies at Navesink, 1885; yal.00039; xxx.00330; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box box 3)
  This manuscript appears to concern the possible arrangement of the eight-poem cycle Fancies at Navesink, which was published in the August 1885 issue of Nineteenth Century. The titles of three poems not included in Fancies at Navesink—After the Supper and Talk, You Lingering Sparse Leaves of Me, and Ah, Not This Granite Dead and Cold—are also mentioned. This manuscript is bound with others under the title Fancies at Navesink.
- Fancies at Navesink, about 1885; yal.00072; xxx.00330; poetry 5 leaves handwritten (Box box 3)
  These five leaves remain from what was originally a six-leaf manuscript (a note at the top of the first leaf reads, in Whitman's hand, "these six pages all one piece") of Fancies at Navesink, an eight-poem cycle which was first published in the August 1885 issue of Nineteenth Century. The poems included are The Pilot in the Mist, Had I the Choice, Last of Ebb, and Daylight Waning, Proudly the Flood Comes In, By That Long Scan of Waves, and Then Last of All. These leaves are bound with others under the title Fancies at Navesink.
- Had I the Choice, about 1885; yal.00073; xxx.00332; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box box 3)
  This manuscript is an early draft of the poem Had I the Choice, published as part of Fancies at Navesink in the August 1885 issue of Nineteenth Century. This manuscript is bound with others under the title Fancies at Navesink.
- Had I the Choice, about 1885; yal.00040; xxx.00332; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box box 3)
  This is a draft of the poem Had I the Choice, published as part of Fancies at Navesink in the August 1885 issue of Nineteenth Century. The leaf is bound with others under the title Fancies at Navesink.
- [waning day], about 1885; yal.00042; xxx.00334; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box box 3)
  This is a revised draft of poetic lines that may be an early version of Last of Ebb, and Daylight Waning, published as part of Fancies at Navesink in the August 1885 issue of Nineteenth Century. On the verso is part of a cancelled letter to Whitman. The leaf is bound with others under the title Fancies at Navesink.
- [Last of ebb, and daylight waning], about 1885; yal.00044; xxx.00334; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box box 3)
  This is a draft of the poem Last of Ebb, and Daylight Waning, published as part of Fancies at Navesink in August 1885 issue of Nineteenth Century. This manuscript is bound with others under the title Fancies at Navesink.
- [Last of ebb, and daylight waning], about 1885; yal.00046; xxx.00334; poetry 3 leaves handwritten (Box box 3)
  This is a draft on three leaves of the poem Last of Ebb, and Daylight Waning, published as part of Fancies at Navesink in the August 1885 issue of Nineteenth Century. The manuscript has the cancelled title At the Mouth of the River. The first leaf is written on the back of a letter from J. M. Rollo, requesting an authograph. This manuscript is bound with others under the title Fancies at Navesink.
- [Nor you alone], about 1885; yal.00049; xxx.00335; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box box 3)
  This is a draft of the poem And Yet Not You Alone, published as part of Fancies at Navesink in the August 1885 issue of Nineteenth Century. The draft also has, in the bottom margin, the title of the poem which follows it in Fancies at Navesink, Proudly the Flood Comes In. This manuscript is bound with others under the title Fancies at Navesink.
- [your needed blending], about 1885; yal.00050; xxx.00335; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box box 3)
  This is a draft of the poem And Yet Not You Alone, published as part of Fancies at Navesink in the August 1885 issue of Nineteenth Century. This manuscript is bound with others under the title Fancies at Navesink.
- [Proudly the flood comes in], about 1885; yal.00052; xxx.00336; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box box 3)
  This is a draft of Proudly the Flood Comes In, published as part of Fancies at Navesink in the August 1885 issue of Nineteenth Century. The verso of this manuscript is an advertisement for Whitman's book, Drum-Taps. This manuscript is bound with others under the title Fancies at Navesink.
- [and deeper still], about 1885; yal.00054; xxx.00338; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box box 3)
  This is a revised draft of the poem Then Last of All, published as part of Fancies at Navesink in the August 1885 issue of Nineteenth Century. This manuscript is bound with others under the title Fancies at Navesink.
- [last—Dec 11], about 1885; yal.00055; xxx.00338; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box box 3)
  This is a revised draft of the poem Then Last of All, published as part of Fancies at Navesink in the August 1885 issue of Nineteenth Century. The verso of this manuscript is an advertisement for Whitman's book, Drum-Taps. This manuscript is bound with others under the title Fancies at Navesink.
- Funeral Interpolations, 1888; yal.00013; xxx.00393; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box box 3)
  This is a signed draft of Funeral Interpolations, a poem published first as Over and Through the Burial Chant in the New York Herald on August 12, 1888, on the occasion of General Philip K. Sheridan's death, and later as Interpolation Sounds in Good-Bye My Fancy ( 1891 ).
- For Queen Victoria's Birthday, about 1890; yal.00032; xxx.00557; poetry 1 leaf handwritten printed (Box box 3)
  This is a typed and corrected proof of For Queen Victoria's Birthday, first published in the Philadelphia Public Ledger on May 24, 1890. Whitman later included this poem in Good-Bye My Fancy ( 1891 ).
- Incidents, for (Soldier in the Ranks), about 1863; yal.00008; xxx.00663; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box box 1, Folder 53)
  This manuscript includes both a description of the aftermath of a Civil War battle and the poem Incidents, for (Soldier in the Ranks), which addresses "the second day of the battle" at Gettysburg.
- Inscription: to the 4th Edition of Leaves of Grass, about 1867; yal.00010; xxx.00024; xxx.00353; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box box 3)
  This is a draft of the poem Inscription, which was first published in the 1867 edition of Leaves of Grass. The poem was later revised and published as One's-Self I Sing. In Leaves of Grass ( 1891–92 ), lines from this manuscript appear in both One's-Self I Sing and Small the Theme of My Chant.
- Italian Music in Dakota, about 1881; yal.00003; xxx.00257; poetry 2 leaves handwritten (Box box 3)
  This is a draft of Italian Music in Dakota, first published in the 1881–82 edition of Leaves of Grass.
- Leaves of Grass advertisements and table of contents, about 1881; yal.00035; xxx.00001; poetry 10 leaves printed handwritten (Box box 3, Folder 155)
  Proofs of the publisher's advertisement and the table of contents for the 1881–82 edition of Leaves of Grass, with corrections and deletions in Whitman's hand.
- The Man-of-War Bird, about 1876; yal.00005; xxx.00134; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box box 3)
  This manuscript is a note by Whitman for the poem To the Man-of-War Bird, which was first published in the April 1, 1876 issue of Athenaeum.
- [names], undated; yal.00015; xxx.00854; prose poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box box 3)
  This is a note in Whitman's handwriting which lists "names," including "the Niam-Niams," "the Battas," "the Tonga-Taboos," and "the Aleuts"; also included in this note is the address of John P. Soule, a Boston "photographer and publisher." The relationship of this note to Whitman's published work is unknown.
- A Night Battle in the late War, 1863; yal.00031; xxx.00502; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 3, Folder 135)
  This is a brief note, dated May 2, 1863 and titled A Night Battle in the late War. The night battle to which this note refers is probably the battle of Chancellorsville. Similar phraseology appeared in Memoranda During the War ( 1875–76 ), in the section headed May 12 —A Night Battle, Over a Week Since.
- Osceola, 1890; yal.00037; xxx.00400; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 3)
  This manuscript is apparently a printer's copy of the poem Osceola, which was first published in Munyon's Illustrated World in April 1890. This manuscript is bound together with others.
- Sands at Seventy, about 1884; yal.00020; xxx.00310; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box box 3)
  This is a note, written on the verso of a postmarked envelope, that offers the title Sands on the Shores of Seventy &c &c for Annex to the preceding, as an alternative to the title Sands at Seventy, which was first used for a cluster of poems in November Boughs ( 1888 ).
- Song of the Universal, 1874; yal.00061; xxx.00123; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box box 3)
  This manuscript is a note in Whitman's hand about the poem Song of the Universal, with the date June 17, 1874. The leaf is bound together with other manuscripts.
- [Come, said the Muse], about 1874; yal.00062; xxx.00123; poetry 2 leaves handwritten (Box box 3)
  Very early draft fragment of Song of the Universal, first published simultaneously in the New York Evening Post and the New York Daily Graphic on June 17, 1874. The manuscript bears the cancelled date " March 31, '74 ." The two leaves are bound together with other manuscripts.
- Song of the Universal, about 1874; yal.00064; xxx.00123; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box box 3)
  Very early draft fragment of Song of the Universal, first published simultaneously in the New York Evening Post and the New York Daily Graphic on June 17, 1874. The leaf is bound together with other manuscripts.
- [all the vast mass], about 1874; yal.00065; xxx.00123; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box box 3)
- [Christ], about 1874; yal.00066; xxx.00123; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box box 3)
- Song of the Universal, June 1874; yal.00068; xxx.00123; poetry 5 leaves handwritten (Box box 3)
  These five leaves make up what is apparently a complete printer's copy of Song of the Universal, first published simultaneously in the New York Evening Post and the New York Daily Graphic on June 17, 1874. The manuscript is dated June 1874. The leaves are bound together with other manuscripts.
- Song of the Universal, about 1874; yal.00069; xxx.00123; poetry 4 leaves handwritten (Box box 3)
  These four leaves make up an early complete draft of Song of the Universal, first published simultaneously in the New York Evening Post and the New York Daily Graphic on June 17, 1874. The four leaves are bound together with other manuscripts.
- [the Idea of All], about 1872; yal.00021; xxx.00267; poetry prose 16 leaves handwritten 6.25 x 3.5 in. (Box box 3, Folder 142)
  These leaves are pages from a top-bound notebook containing draft lines of poetry, apparently for a poem delivered at the Dartmouth College commencement in June 1872 and first published under the title, As a Strong Bird on Pinions Free, later revised and published as Thou Mother with Thy Equal Brood. Many of the pages have been cut out or trimmed, and seven envelope faces have been attached at the back of the notebook.
- Rise, Lurid Stars, about 1865; yal.00011; xxx.00203; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box box 3)
  This is a poem draft, the last three lines of which were later revised and published in Drum-Taps ( 1865 ) as World Take Good Notice and included in subsequent editions of Leaves of Grass. On the verso of this draft is a prose fragment discussing slavery and Southern aristocracy.
- Sea Captains, Young or Old, about 1873; yal.00006; xxx.00139; poetry 2 leaves handwritten (Box box 3)
  This manuscript is a signed draft of Sea Captains, Young or Old, which was published first in the New York Daily Graphic on April 4, 1873. The poem was later retitled, Song for All Seas, All Ships, and appeared in Two Rivulets, the companion volume to the 1876 Author's edition of Leaves of Grass.
- [I cross'd the Nevadas], about 1865; yal.00009; xxx.00178; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box box 3)
  These six lines make up a draft of Rise O Days from Your Fathomless Deeps, which was published in Drum-Taps in 1865 and in subsequent editions of Leaves of Grass.
- To the Year 1889, about 1889; yal.00007; xxx.00389; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box box 3)
  This is a late draft of To the Year 1889, published first on January 5, 1889, in the Critic. Retitled To the Pending Year, the poem appeared in Good-Bye My Fancy in 1891.
- The Unexpress'd, 1890; yal.00012; xxx.00407; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box box 3)
  This is a draft of The Unexpress'd, which was published in Lippincott's Magazine in March 1891. A note on the manuscript in Whitman's hand indicates that the poem was sent for publication in 1890 to W. H. Alden, the editor of Harper's Monthly Magazine, but was rejected.
- A Voice from Death, June 1889; yal.00060; xxx.00401; poetry 5 leaves handwritten (Box box 3)
  This is a signed manuscript of A Voice from Death, a poem written in response to the Johnstown, Pennsylvania, flood in the spring of 1889 in which 2,000 people died after a dam collapsed following torrential rains. This poem was published on June 7, 1889, in the New York World. The manuscript is the printer's copy and each page is mounted separately and bound in a volume with a lettered title page and a portrait frontispiece by E. Whittlesey Kotz.
- with husky-haughty lips, O sea, 1884; yal.00002; xxx.00340; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box box 3, Folder 170)
  This is a draft of With Husky-Haughty Lips, O Sea!, first published in Harper's Monthly Magazine in March 1884, written on the verso of a discarded review of John Burrough's Notes on Walt Whitman. This poem was reprinted in the Sands at Seventy annex to Leaves of Grass in 1888 and after.
- with husky-haughty lips, O Sea!, 1884; yal.00001; xxx.00340; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box box 3)
  This is a signed and revised draft of With Husky-Haughty Lips, O Sea!, which was published first in Harper's Monthly Magazine in March 1884. This poem was reprinted in the Sands at Seventy annex to Leaves of Grass in 1888 and after.
- With Husky-Haughty Lips, O Sea!, 1884; yal.00034; xxx.00340; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box box 3)
  This is a printed draft of the poem, With Husky-Haughty Lips, O Sea!, with corrections in Whitman's hand. The poem was published first in Harper's Monthly Magazine in March 1884, and was reprinted in the Sands at Seventy annex to Leaves of Grass in 1888 and after.
- With Husky-Haughty Lips, O Sea!, 1884; yal.00036; xxx.00340; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box box 3)
  This is a printed draft of the poem, With Husky-Haughty Lips, O Sea!, with corrections in Whitman's hand. The poem was published first in Harper's Monthly Magazine in March 1884, and was reprinted in the Sands at Seventy annex to Leaves of Grass in 1888 and later.
- [While I so deeply loved], 1864; yal.00150; xxx.00193; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 56)
  This is a manuscript with poem notes relating to Whitman's experience as a nurse during the Civil War, some lines of which correspond to The Wound-Dresser, first published in Leaves of Grass ( 1876 ). The verso contains notes about a call Whitman received from a mother, dated December 23, 1864, regarding her son Frank Lester, an imprisoned soldier. The relationship of these prose notes to Whitman's published work is unknown.
- Pictures, about 1855; yal.00081; xxx.00259; xxx.00614; poetry 27 leaves handwritten (Box 3, Folder 137)
  Bound draft of a poem unpublished in Whitman's lifetime, titled "Pictures." The first several lines of draft were revised and published as My Picture-Gallery in The American in October 1880.
- Memoranda of a Year, 1863; yal.00346; xxx.00524; xxx.00502; xxx.00993; prose 9 leaves handwritten printed (Box 3, Folder 143)
  Draft of letter, heavily revised, to publisher James Redpath. Included with the letter, which pitches Whitman's idea for a book about his firsthand experiences among Civil War soldiers, are a title page mock-up, a draft publisher's announcement, the label that Whitman created for these items, and a blank envelope. The letter is written on the reverse of proofs of a circular for the United States Christian Commission, and the label, which dates the letter to October 21, 1863, is written on the clipped front of a United States Christian Commission envelope. Whitman was unable to get such a book published for over a decade. Memoranda During the War ( 1875–76 ) includes the short essay A New Army Organization Fit for America Needed, which echoes specifically the ideas and language about military reform from the draft letter. This essay was later shortened to a single paragraph and republished in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–83 ), given the slightly altered title A New Army Organization Fit for America. The same language from the letter draft might also have contributed to a note on the topic of military reform that Whitman added to Democratic Vistas ( 1871 ) when he created that book-length essay from several earlier pieces.
- [Immense numbers (several thousands)], 1865; yal.00149; xxx.00481; prose 1 leaf handwritten printed (Box 1, Folder 55)
  A draft fragment of Small Memoranda, first published in November Boughs ( 1888 ).
- Brooklyn, Jan 19 & 20, 1865, yal.00152; xxx.00502; xxx.00855; xxx.00856; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 56)
  Whitman's response to learning of George Whitman's imprisonment at Danville during the Civil War. This manuscript contains much of the same information about George and his status as a prisoner of war that Whitman published in A Brooklyn Soldier, and A Noble One, which appeared in the 19 January 1865 issue of the Brooklyn Daily Eagle. Material in this manuscript also contributed to The Fifty-first New-York Volunteers, published in the New-York Times, 24 January 1865 as well as portions of Memoranda During the War ( 1875–76 ).
- [mention with honor Capt Daniel E Jenkins], 1864–1865; yal.00169; xxx.00856; prose 1 leaf handwritten printed (Box 1, Folder 57)
  A short piece of Civil War memoranda that contributed to a portion of The Fifty-first New-York Volunteers, published in the 24 January 1865 issue of the New-York Times.
- [Martin Weaver], 1864–1865; yal.00171; xxx.00856; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 57)
  A scrap of Whitman's Civil War memoranda. His notes on Robert B. Potter and Edward Ferrero were used in The Fifty-first New-York Volunteers, which appeared in the 24 January 1865 issue of the New-York Times.
- [deserter arrested election day], 1864–1865; yal.00172; xxx.00857; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 57)
  Notes and memoranda of the Civil War, some of which contributed to Fifty-first New-York City Veterans, published in the 29 October 1864 issue of the New-York Times.
- [51st N Y V], 1864–1865; yal.00173; xxx.00856; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 57)
  A scrap of Civil War memoranda headed "51st N Y V" in which Whitman mentions the death of Captain Daniel E. Jenkins. Whitman wrote about Jenkins in The Fifty-first New-York Volunteers, which appeared in the 24 January 1864 issue of the New-York Times.
- [some interesting items of 51st], 1864; yal.00185; xxx.00856; xxx.00857; xxx.00859; prose 16 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder 57)
  A notebook on the 51st New York Veterans in which Whitman recorded notes on George W. Whitman and other soldiers in that regiment, including their involvement in the war and snippets of biographical information. While significant passages from this notebook cannot be found verbatim in Whitman's published work, it is clear that these notes contributed to Whitman's Civil War writings, including Fifty-first New-York City Veterans, New-York Times, 29 October 1864; Fifty-first New-York Volunteers, New-York Times, 24 January 1865; and Return of a Brooklyn Veteran, Brooklyn Daily Union, 16 March 1865.
- [Jan 21, 1865, New York], yal.00186; xxx.00856; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 57)
  Notes from Whitman's interview with E. F. Shephard regarding officers of the 51st New-York Volunteers. Portions of this manuscript were used in The Fifty-first New-York Volunteers, New-York Times, 24 January 1865.
- [In acc't of 51st], 1864; yal.00211; xxx.00857; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 58)
  A small scrap of paper with Whitman's notes on the 51st New-York Veterans, his account of which was published in the 29 October 1864 issue of the New-York Times as Fifty-first New-York City Veterans.
- [Frank Butler was from Massachusetts], 1864–1865; yal.00212; xxx.00855; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 58)
  Whitman's notes on Frank Butler, an officer of the 51st New-York Veterans who died in action. Whitman wrote about Butler's death in A Brooklyn Soldier, and a Noble One, which appeared in the 19 January 1865 issue of the Brooklyn Daily Eagle.
- [It has been good fun], 1872; yal.00317; xxx.00860; prose 3 leaves handwritten (Box 3, Folder 110)
  Draft of a prose piece which appeared in the 17 October 1872 issue of the Washington Evening Star, under the head Washington News and Gossip. For more on this manuscript and its contribution to this published work, see Martin G. Murray, Walt Whitman Laughs: An Uncollected Piece of Prose Journalism, Walt Whitman Quarterly Review 30 (Winter 2013), 138-149.
- Real American Red Men, 1870–1872; yal.00324; xxx.00861; prose 2 leaves handwritten (Box 3, Folder 116)
  Draft of a prose piece which appeared in the 20 September 1872 issue of the Washington Evening Star, under the head Washington News and Gossip. For more on this manuscript and its historical context, see Martin Murray, The Poet-Chief Greets the Sioux, Walt Whitman Quarterly Review 17 (Summer 1999), 25-37.
- Washington as a Central Winter Residence, 1871–1872; yal.00328; xxx.00862; prose 6 leaves handwritten (Folder 119)